I've covered Dr Lane Norton a few times
here on the old physionic and this time
I ran across a video whereing he's asked
about his three Mount Rushmore
supplements as in supplements that he'd
recommend to almost everyone now for
Mount Rushmore there should be four
since there's four heads on Mount
Rushmore but he only mentions three so
I'll add another to make it four anyway
if you don't know Dr Norton he earned
his PhD in nutrition science and he's
quite vocal about being science-based in
his work so without further Ado here's
what Dr Norton has to say what are
supplements that everybody should have
in their stack on average do you think
what are the supplements that really
work okay so I kind of like Branch these
into like tear right so my Mount
Rushmore of supplements would be uh
creatin monohydrate would be number one
um dosage frequency
five grams a day there may be evidence
that like 10 or even maybe a little bit
more has cognitive benefits Tim Farris
been talking about that yeah so it's
very safe I mean there are people who
have been hand ringing about creatin for
a long time and the the worst thing that
you can say about it is people say well
causes hair loss okay we'll get to the
hair loss part but let's address the
beginning the first supplement is
creatine especially creatine monohydrate
now I wholeheartedly agree monohydrate
is the cheapest form and it works just
as well as any other formulation also
it's been shown to be effective across a
range of studies in relation to muscle
mass muscle growth muscle performance
but then lane or Dr nordon mentions it
might have an effect on the brain and
that's also true I covered those studies
extensively I'll link my work for you
this is especially true for older
indivual uals those over the age of 60
or so okay but what about the hair loss
part no there was a single study in 2009
that soed creatin supplementation
increased DHT that is not the same thing
as showing hair loss DHT is a marker and
that is a mechanism now that's never
been replicated and they didn't show a
viable mechanism by which it does it
because the the the their test
testosterone levels didn't change which
is the precursor and then the in the the
the product after DHT didn't change so
either creatin is having some direct
effect on this enzyme or this is a data
artifact that has not been replicated
like Dr Norton said that idea came out
due to this study where in creatin
consumers experienced a significant
increase in the molecule called
dihydrotestosterone or DH h t for short
I remember looking into this a number of
years ago and there were some mechanisms
that were proposed contrary to Dr
Norton's take here the idea was that DHT
levels rise and DHT has a potent effect
at miniaturizing the hair follicle now
the reason it only happens on the head
is because the enzyme that produces DHT
comes into isoforms or different
versions and the scalp one is the one
that's affected by creatine now to be
clear this is taking several leaps based
on a single short-term study and it's
true there are no direct assessments of
hair loss with creatine
supplementation now I'd love to tell you
that we have definitive evidence one way
or another but we don't there's even a
study that was in the works to address
that question but I see that the funding
was withdrawn so the study is no longer
in progress big bald is putting up the
roadblocks anyway I wouldn't worry about
the hair loss part and although Lane
doesn't mention this I Kidney Health is
another fear for many yet I covered that
as well there's no concern according to
this study and I go over more on my
video on that topic I mean look how
concerned I look in the thumbnail I mean
clearly you have to watch it and one
final thing Dr Norton says which I
co-sign completely I'm not saying
everybody should be on it
but it is a lowcost high yield
supplement that is very safe and we're
not talking about a couple studies we
are talking about thousands of studies
done over decades in Labs all over the
world I am very confident in fact I was
so amazed by creatine's effects that I
wrote a book about it detailing over 100
studies now I don't sell it anymore but
it is included for the physionic
Insiders along with all my perks like
the podcast uh full library of videos
and more so it's linked in the
description box if you're so inclined
okay let's jump to the next Mount Rush
more supplement now caffeine caffeine is
the original neut Tropic it is the
original performance enhancer um and if
you look at the benefits of caffeine
increases cognitive performance
increases exercise performance um
downsides negatively impact sleep so if
you're going to take it do it earlier in
the day okay the second is caffeine now
I would actually slightly change that
mention and I'll explain why in a minute
but overall yes caffeine is a cognitive
benefit and it's a performance benefit
I've covered that in the past as well
which shall also be linked for you but I
covered studies like these wherein
people who consume caffeine tended to
outperform those that don't if that's
endurance exercise like running or even
resistance training performance I also
agree that timing caffeine is important
because it can lead to detrimental
effects in that it affects sleep so
generally I have my own cut off point
consuming it only in the morning um as
far as dosage I mean you get some anti-
fatigue benefits like 50 100 milligrams
you get start to get the performance
benefits once you get up around two 300
milligrams of caffeine like for
exercise strength benefits like acute
strength benefit are more like 3 to 600
migs of caffeine Christ yeah that's a
lot of caffeine and he's right in this
review they mentioned the benefits start
to occur around 1.5 milligram per
kilogram of body weight when it comes to
resistance training the endurance
benefits might be a bit lower you can
see why consuming it earlier in the day
is important to preserve sleep
especially on that high of doses before
we go on to the third supplement I'd
like to Circle back as the cons
insulting world would say and mention
that the molecule caffeine has all these
effects but the greater benefit probably
comes from the other compounds that come
along with it like health benefits we've
been focused on performance but the
health benefits of caffeine probably
more so come from the other molecules
that come along for the ride like
polyphenols that you'd find in black
coffee or even some teas so it's one
distinction that I think can make
caffeine from yeah it's a good idea for
performance and mental stimulation to
it's great for health as well I have a
very fun video on that topic that I'll
link for you and yes the title is
sarcastic and I really had a blast with
that one anyway moving on uh creatin
caffeine whey protein uh whey protein
tasty relatively cheap
soluble um been shown to improve body
composition numerous times it's not
magic it's just a very tasty kind of
ubiquitous form of protein that's highly
bioavailable so the final supplement
that Dr Norton mentions is whey protein
he mentions that it has a weight loss or
fat loss effect and that's true as many
many Studies have indicated that whey
protein does exactly that however I
don't think it's because there's
anything magical about whey and rather
just a substantial increase in the most
potent satiating nutrient protein so
could these effects be had at least to
some extent by simply upping your
protein intake yeah probably still it's
true that it's generally pretty cheap
and works well even if it isn't magical
I mean for example creatine earlier is
literal fairy dust I kid of course but
the benefits are not as easily had
unlike whey protein where other protein
sources could offer the majority of the
same benefits so is it a musthave
supplement not at all although it can be
very helpful and has mostly positives to
its name now as I mentioned that's not
exactly a Mount Rushmore considering
it's three not four so if I can add one
I'd add omega-3 fats this is another one
like creatine that has more research
releasing that it may benefit multiple
organ systems one the heart but also the
brain I have many videos opening the
studies and actually explaining the data
and the mechanisms I'll link uh those
for you as well that said this is
another one that could probably be
replaced by actual food and may not be
necessary for everyone for example
eating fatty fish just a few times per
week May reduce the need for
supplementation and it isn't limited to
fish sources it can also come from algae
sources so long as they're Omega-3s so
overall what's the takeaway here well I
like Dr Norton's perspective on these I
largely agree with his points and I
think a few things I'd frame differently
but overall solid choices in the end no
supplement is necessary but these three
or four creatine caffeine ESP especially
in coffee or tea form with polyphenols
co-consumed whey protein and Omega-3s
are a great base and if you aren't
interested in weight loss or already
consume a lot of protein I'd even save
your money on skipping wheight protein
honestly there's plenty more to be said
on each of these but I'll leave the more
detailed discussions for some of my
other work which is linked below as well
as here and really if you like horrible
jokes this one is particularly funny
[Music]